Guide to the Nora H. Faires Papers, 1854-2010 AIS.2011.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Nora H. Faires Papers
1854-2010
1970-2006
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Faires, Nora Helen
AIS.2011.06
3.9 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Dr. Nora H. Faires was a History professor at Western Michigan University in Kalamazoo, Michigan, who received her doctorate in History from the University of Pittsburgh in 1981. Her collection contains research files that she used in the creation of her dissertation, as well as other works, and deals primarily with German populations and churches in the cities of Pittsburgh and Allegheny. Such information includes parish histories, data and notes on churches in the 19th century, census records and sample drafts of papers and chapters.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Linda Pritchard in 2011.
Scope and Content Notes
The Nora H. Faires Papers present a broad sketch of the academic career of Dr. Faires. The bulk of her research and documentation concerns German congregations that are located within the Pittsburgh region and was the subject of her dissertation. Included in her papers are a variety of primary sources from the congregations, as well as her own notes and thoughts. She was planning on revisiting the churches of Pittsburgh in a book, The Splintered Cross, with much of her research re-examining the congregations she had looked at in her dissertation. Thus, there is some overlap in research between these two series, though the research she gained in The Splintered Cross is different from that of her dissertation. However, the files for The Splintered Cross project contain a variety of primary sources along with many of her notes which provide a variety of information on the topic but also a window into the creative process.
While the bulk of Dr. Faires papers represent her research on the German immigrant community, it does not include her research materials on the various subjects represented by her academic publications, such as the Great Lakes region, Canada and African-Americans. They do however contain a variety of academic papers she presented throughout her career, which serves to give a broader sense of her academic interests.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following six series:
Series I. Dissertation Research
Series II. Correspondence and Peer Reviews
Series III. Presentations and Academic Papers
Series IV. Other Research
Series V. The Splintered Cross
Series VI. Audio/Visual Material
Biography
Dr. Nora H. Faires' academic career spanned more than three decades. During that time she worked as a professor and advisor in addition to publishing four books, while spending much of the last months of her life working on a manuscript for a fifth.
Growing up in Sharpsville, Mercer County, Pennsylvania, Faires attended the University of Pittsburgh for both her graduate and undergraduate academic career. She wrote her dissertation on German immigrant communities and congregations in western Pennsylvania in the mid to late 19th century, which was entitled, Ethnicity in Evolution: The German community in Pittsburgh and Allegheny City, Pennsylvania 1845-1885. Her interest in immigration can be traced through her personal family history. Following her birth, her family immigrated from Ontario, Canada to Pennsylvania. After earning her doctorate from Pitt in 1981, she would go on to teach at the University of Puget Sound, University of Texas at Arlington before settling on a more permanent position at the University of Michigan-Flint, where she taught from 1982-1999. In 2000, Dr. Faires began teaching at Western Michigan University (WMU) where she was influential in the creation of a Canadian Studies program. In 2007, Dr. Faires was promoted to the position of professor of history and of gender and women's studies at WMU.
Dr. Faires worked on numerous books over her lifetime, including Permeable Border: The Great Lakes Basin as Transnational Region, 1650–1990, and Jewish Life in the Industrial Promised Land, 1855–2005. She also won two American Historical Association prizes in her lifetime; the 1995 William Gilbert Award and the 2006 Albert B. Corey Prize. Her final project left uncompleted at the time of her death was a book on German Communities in the Pittsburgh region titled The Splintered Cross. Nora Faires died on February 6, 2011, after a 15 year battle with breast cancer.
Previous Citation
Nora H. Faires Papers, 1854-2010, AIS.2011.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
First German Methodist Episcopal Church, Birmingham, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records AIS.1974.24, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
First Trinity Evangelical Church Records, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1837-1975, AIS.1975.04, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Grace Reformed Church, Pittsburgh, Pa.,1853-1964, AIS.1968.21, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Smithfield Congregational Church Records, Pittsburgh, Pa. 1832-1971; AIS.1974.25, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
St. John's Evangelical Lutheran Church Records, AIS.1990.08, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
St. Matthew's Lutheran Church Records, 1873-1936, AIS.1974.27,Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Zion Evangelical Lutheran Church, Lawrencewille, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1868-1988, AIS.1988.03, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Personal papers; Research notes; Correspondence; Lutheran Church -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; German Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Religion; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- History -- 19th century; Germans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Churches and Synagogues; Congregational churches -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Smithfield Congregational Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Smithfield United Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); St. John's German Evangelical Lutheran Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); St. Matthew's Lutheran Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); First Trinity Evangelical Lutheran Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Smithfield United Church of Christ (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Faires, Nora Helen
- Dissertation Research, 1913-1987; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the bulk of research files and notes that were necessary in crafting Dr. Faires Dissertation "Ethnicity in Evolution: The German Community in Pittsburgh and Allegheny City, Pennsylvania, 1845-1885", which was completed in 1981. The information is quite diverse, including not only primary documents from the churches themselves but many of the notes and thoughts of Dr. Faires herself. While the dissertation itself is not present, and there are few drafts and samples, the entirety of it is available from the University of Pittsburgh Library System.
  - Research Files and Data Sets, 1868-1982; 1.
    Dr. Faires did a large amount of background reading and supplemental research in the creation of her dissertation, as well as several small exerpts from the dissertation itself. Included here are many of the surveys and regional research Dr. Faires examined. Present here is the information that she would use to help define the relationship of Pittsburgh's churches to one another, as well as categorize their beliefs and ideological stands. It also contains her examination into the cities of Pittsburgh and Allegheny in the mid-19th century, and contains city and census records. Also present are her outlines and research plans, showing how she not only conducted her research, but how she planned and directed it as well.
    - 25 Successful Germans, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1850 Census information on PA German churches, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - 5 Cities Occupation Codes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The 48ers of Watertown, Wisconsin, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Addenda to Tables, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Agricultural Revolution in Germany, c1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Allegheny City Social Statistics, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Arndt Olson--German-American Newspapers, c1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bank and Insurance Company Advertisements 1865-1887, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Banks and Insurance Companies from the Pittsburgh City Directory 1857-1877, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Census of U.S. Cities, Principle Cities and Towns, 1850-1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Church Data Overview, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Church Member Data, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Comments on Dissertation: Bob Doherty, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Comments on Dissertation: Larry Glasco, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Comments on Dissertation: Fred Luebke, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Comments on Dissertation: Robert P. Swierenga, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Comments on Dissertation: Phil VanderMeer, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Data on 19th Century German Upper Class, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Dissertation Abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Dissertation Introduction, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Disseration Tables, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Documentation on Manuscript Census Files (1850-1870), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Ethnicity: The Vital Center of Religion in America" by Harry S. Stout, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Ethnicity: The Skeleton of Religion in America", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Freihetis Freund & Notes (German), c1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - General Congregational Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "German Achievements in America", by Rudolf Cronau, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Germans in Pittsburgh and Allegheny Outline and Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - German Jews, Data and Notes, c1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - German Singing Societies Data and Notes, c1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Germans Living in America (German), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - German Socialists Notes, c1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "The German Upper Class in Pittsburgh" by Layne Peiffer, c1964 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "The Good Provider: H.J. Heinz and His 57 Varieties" by Robert C. Alberts, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Jefferson Lodge Booklet, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Jefferson Lodge Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - List of Pittsburgh's German Newspapers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous Sources Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Occupational Dichotomy Derived from Church Records, c1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Outline of Dissertation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Parish Data Available for Each Congregation, c1974 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Pennsylvania Magazine, "The Buena Vista Affair", c1964 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - The Place of Methodism in the Religous Life of the Pittsburgh Region, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Pittsburgh and Allegheny Occupation Codes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Pittsburgh and Allegheny Street Directories, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Pittsburgh 1860 Census Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - "Pittsburgh City Government 1816-1850" by John W. Dankosky, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Pittsburgh Regional Economic Development, c1967 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Pittsburgh Social Statistics at the Census of 1880, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Preliminary Tables on Immigrant Wealth and Occupation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Religious Variable Codes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Research Plan and Notes, c1974 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Ruth Salisbury Exerpts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Carolyn S. Schumacher Research on Children in Pittsburgh, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Ship Passenger Lists Notes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Sources Available in Germany and Notes, c1975 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Social Structural Analysis and Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - SPSS Religions Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Tables and Figures Regarding Churches, Undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Unpublished Dissertations List, c1980 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Autobiographies, 1938-1978; 2.
    A great deal of information was gleaned by Dr. Faires from examining the lives of German-American missionaries and church founders. This subseries contains their autobiographies, which give insight not only into their own lives, but into the spiritual life of the region itself. Many of them are quite lengthy, and describe decades of work within the religious communities in the Pittsburgh area. Also present are Dr. Faires own notes which help to evaluate and examine the sources.
    - C. Golder [German Methodist], Undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Jacob Haller [Evangelical Association], 1978 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Christian Kirst, Undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Rev. John Launitz [German Presbyterian], c1974 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Adam Miller, "Experience of German Methodist Preachers", 1859 (Box 1, Folder 68-70)
    - Bishop Michael O'Connor [Roman Catholic], Undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Gerhard Oncken [Baptist], Undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Frederick Ruoff [German Evangelical Protestant], Undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - J.H.W. Stuckenberg Biography [Lutheran], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 74-75)
    - Carl Walther [Lutheran], Undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Peter Paul Cahensly [Roman Catholic], 1978 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Congregational Histories and Data, 1885-1987; 3.
    In her dissertation Dr. Faires identified several major congregations in which she would examine: Smithfield Congregational Church (Smithfield United Church of Christ today), First German Methodist (now defunct), Zion Evangelical (Albright Community United Methodist Church today), St. Matthew's Lutheran, St. John's Evangelical Lutheran, First German Baptist, and First Trinity Evangelical Lutheran. Located here is the treasure trove of information on these churches in the mid-19th century. Included are parish histories, copies of church documents and ledgers, as well as volumes of notes by Dr. Faires. The information between the churches is not balanced however, as there is significantly more information for some churches such as Smithfield, over others like First Trinity Evangelical Lutheran. Still, there is a truly staggering amount of information present, and anyone interested in Pittsburgh during this time period (circa 1850) would gain a tremendous information about the German-American religious community.
    - English Lutheran Church, c1973 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Evangelical Lutheran Church of Western Pennsylvania, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - First German Methodist Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - First St. John's Lutheran Church Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - First Trinity [Missouri Synod] Lutheran, Undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - German Methodist Members 1856-1859, Undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - German Presbyterian Records and Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Grace Reformed Data and Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - German Catholic Churches, Data and Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Immanuel United Methodist Church 120th Anniversary, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - St. Paul's Evangelical, c1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Pittsburgh Lutheran Planning Study, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Pittsburgh Synod History, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Smithfield: Records and Pamphlets, 1850-1930 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Smithfield: Voss' History (German), Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - St. John's Evangelical Lutheran Church: Parish History and Jubilee Program, c1913 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - St. John's Ohio Lutheran Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - St. Matthews Lutheran Church Notes, c1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - St. Mary's Catholic Data, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - St. Paul's: Memorial History (German) and Pamphlets, 1933-1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - St. Peter's:Charter, Membership Book, and Diamond Anniversary, 1885-1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - St. Peter's and St. Paul's Joint Pictoral Directory and Notes, c1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Temple Baptist Church: Church History (German) and Anniversary booklets, 1913-1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Temple Baptist Church: A Brief History, c1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Trinity Missouri Synod: History and Data, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Zion Evangelical: 125th Anniversary Booklet, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - First German Methodist Congregational Messenger, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - German Methodist Member List, c1869 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Organizational Histories and Data, 1885-1974; 4.
    In addition to researching various congregations in the Pittsburgh region Dr. Faires also examined several organizations of German immigrants, such as the Catholic Knights of St. George and the Teutonia Mannerchor. Within this series is the data she collected on these organizations. While the intellectual history on some of the organizations is slim, there are primary sources present which provide a great deal of information about the organizations.
    - 46th National Sangerfest, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Catholic Knights of St. George, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Swabian Beneficial Union Records, 1885-1889 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Teutonia Mannerchor Booklet (German), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Correspondence and Peer Reviews, 1982-2007; II.
  During her academic career Dr. Faires was in contact with many other colleagues concerning her research and theirs. This series contains much of this correspondence concerning Dr. Faires' research, as well as her thoughts on the work of her colleagues. Of special note is the review Dr. Faires did of the manuscript on the history of Milwaukee. These provide not only some useful information on Faires' own opinions of the work by other academics, but on the dialogue of the creative process.
  - re: "Evolution of Ethnicity", c1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - re: German Baptists, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - re: German Methodists, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - re: Gender/Citizenship in Modern History Class Syllabus, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Peer Review of History of Milwaukee, c2006 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Rev. Edward McSweeney, c1989 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Southwestern Pennsylvania Synod, c1989 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Elizabeth Waltman, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Presentations and Academic Papers, 1972-1988; III.
  In addition to her published works Dr. Faires also presented papers at various conferences througouht her lifetime. The topics of these papers often related to German immigrant communities as well as religous diversity and the role of women in society. She also presented a paper that would eventually become her unfinished manuscript The Splintered Cross. These papers give help to shawcase her professional activty over her career.
  - "Evolution of Religious Diversity in an Immigrant Community", 1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Ethnicity in Evolution", Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Germans and Cities", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "The Germans in Pittsburgh in 1860", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "German Women and Assimilation", c1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Kinship Relations Among German Immigrants", c1984 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Revolutionaries in a Rationalist Church", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "The Splintered Cross", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "Urban Perspective on Evangelicalism", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Other Research, 1888-2010; IV.
  While much of her research focused on the topic of German immigrant communities, Dr. Faires also worked on a variety of related subjects as well. She kept this work separate from that of her dissertation files and other published works. It encompasses a wide variety of topics with some common themes. These include information on the city of Pittsburgh itself and its role in the shaping of American society, as well as other immigrant communities such as the Irish that settled in Pittsburgh. It also details some of her examination into religious communities and some research into hymnology. It is apparent she did not intend to use this information directly in her work on The Splintered Cross, despite the seeming interrelatedness of some of the material. While this series contains a good deal of eclectic information, the data on any given topic is not great, but it gives a broad survey of information that was clearly important in Dr. Faires life.
  - "A Guide to Old Economy" by Daniel B. Reibel, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - A History of the Catholic Church in Allegheny and Pittsburgh, c2006 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Allegheny County: A Sesqui-Centennial Review, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Allegheny County: It's Early History, c2006 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - The Allegheny City Cotton Mill Riot of 1848, c1963 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Allegheny City Society Reporter Dispatch, c1970 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - American Ethnic Geography, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Annals of Southwestern Pennsylvania, c2007 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Baptist Chronicle, Undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Bestor, "Backwoods Utopias", c1970 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - The Battle of Bushy Run Exerpts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Centenary Memorial of the Planting and Growth of Presbyterianism in Western Pennsylvania and Parts Adjacent, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Dahlinger, "Where the Red Volleys Poured", Undated (Box 2, Folder 55-56)
  - Friesen--An Additional Source on the Harmony Society, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - German American Annals, "The Harmony Society", c1904 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - "German Emigration to the United States: A Review Essay", 1986 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - German Baptists, c2007 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - The Germans in Allegheny 1850-1860, c1971 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Harmony Society for Young Ladies, c1976 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Harmony Society Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Lincoln Papers Exerpts Regarding Pittsburgh, c2006 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Methodist Episcopal 1884 Church Minutes, c2007 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Missouri Germans, c1986 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "Now Thank We all Our God" Hymnology, c1996 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - On Wilhelm Keil, c1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pittsburgh Ephemera, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh Research Facilities Contacts, c2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pittsburgh and Allegheny in the Centennial Year, c2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Pittsburgh Wool Company, c2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Re: The Civil War, c2007 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rimenschneider, "My Life", c2007 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Shiras, "The Iron City", 1929 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sidney Rigdon, c2007 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Social Mirror, c2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Smithfield Windows Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Technischer Verein and Notes, c1888 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Teutonia Mannerchor Record Book (German), 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - William Henry Burleigh Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Walsh, "Irish in Pittsburgh", Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - WPHN References, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Zur Entstehungsgeschichte (German), c2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- The Splintered Cross, 1854-2010; V.
  Dr. Faires final project, The Splintered Cross, was to become a book on the religious diversity of German immigrant communities in Pittsburgh and the relationship of those communities within the development of 19th century American society. Faires worked on this project off and on for nearly the entire breadth of her academic career and remains unfinished. This series represents this work and contains a berth of primary sources on churches in Pittsburgh, as well as information on their relationship with the broader American society. Present are a wide variety of church documents such as pamphlets and brochures as well as marriage records and copied pages of ledgers. Also included are sample drafts of chapters from her book, as well as annotated outlines, research plans, bibliographies and many other guides which show how she planned to construct the book.